Spanish with Juan is a podcast
in Spanish to learn Spanish.
If you have an intermediate or upper-intermediate level of
Spanish, our podcast can help you improve
your comprehension and learn grammar
and vocabulary in context, in a natural way,
listening to Juan's comments and
fun stories.
Guys, guys!  How are you,
how are you?  How's everything going?
Welcome, welcome, and welcome to a new
episode of Spanish with Juan, Spanish with me.
This is a podcast... well, a video, a
video-podcast for Spanish students.
It's a video podcast in Spanish
to learn Spanish, okay?
How are you?  How's everything going?  Guys,
I'm... I'm a little... I'm
spending a few days a little... I'm a little busy.
I'm busy.  Tied up.  Liado means that I have
a lot, a lot, of problems
of many different kinds.
I'm in Italy, and I'm in a house that's not my
house, and I can't find a place to make videos,
to make the podcast.  There is a lot of noise, these
days it is a holiday here in Italy, and it is a little
difficult for me to work, to find a place.
I found this site here, but it's a bit...
well, it's full of stuff, it's full
of junk, isn't it?  About things, about... Well,
look, this umbrella.  This umbrella here...
It's all full of stuff.  But anyway,
it's the only place I've found to...
(Let's see, I'll put the camera like this...)
Of course, if you're listening to this
video podcast, you're not seeing anything.
But I assure you there is a lot of junk.
Look, look how much junk there is around here!
Look at all this junk, huh?  Junk
is stuff that... Look: a closet, plants,
plants everywhere... there are
lots of plants.  Well, a lot...
Oh, a cat!  Look at a cat there... Do you
see it?  There is a cat.  There's a cat there too.
I think he wants to go out, right?  Do you want to go out?   Her
name is Penelope.  This cat is called Penelope.
I'm going to leave it... Wait a
minute... Penny, her name is... Aha!
Okay... There it is.  The cat has gone out.  The
cat is out, okay?  It's on the street.
And that way I'm calmer, right?
Look how much junk
there is here.  The clothes, the clothes hanging out to dry...
In short, it's not the ideal place to make
a podcast, a professional video.  It
is not a study.  It's not what
I was looking for, but... oh well.
The washing machine, with the plant on top...
There's a plant on top of the washing machine!
Guys, I'm going to sit down.  I'm going to try to
calm down, because I'm a little nervous,
okay?  I'm a little nervous, really, because... You ca
n't work like this, you
really can't work.
(And this umbrella... I'm going to remove it. But I
think it gives it color, right? It gives color to this...)
Anyway.  There is an umbrella.  People who are
listening to me but not watching me don't know
what I'm talking about.  I'm talking
about an umbrella.  There is an umbrella here.
A red umbrella, with white polka dots (with
white dots, with white polka dots) that doesn't make
any sense, but it gives color
to the video, doesn't it?  gives color to the video.
Anyway, guys...
How are you?  How,
how is everything going?  I hope, I hope subjunctive,
I hope subjunctive everything goes well for you.
Not for me, eh, I'm not doing well for
many reasons, for many reasons.
Look at what hair, what hair I have, what hair.
Let's see, ah, ah, look, a surprise,
a surprise, a surprise.
I have new glasses, guys, I have new glasses.
Look, look at those glasses.
Mm, I used to have... wait
a minute... I don't know if you, I don't know if
you remember, I used to have glasses.   I do
n't know where it is... I had... I don't know where
I put them, I don't know where I put them,
but I had other glasses before, right?  More... Wait
a minute, wait a minute, yes, yes, yes, yes,
wait, wait, wait, yes,
I think they are, they are here.
Let's see, in this bag, in this paper bag,
in this paper bag I have, I have the glasses.
Some... glasses, my usual glasses
, right?  My usual glasses.
Let's see, eh, eh, stop, so that,
so that you can see the difference, right?
I used to wear, I used to wear these glasses.
Hm, they were, I think, more subtle, weren't they?  More
subtle, aren't they?
Uh, and now,
now I've bought these black glasses.
Hey, I don't think they're bad for me, right?   They have
told me, they have told me that I am better,
that these glasses fit me, that they fit me better.
Yo, what do you want me to tell you?  I
'm not sure, huh?  I'm not sure.   I
see well, I see well, I see quite
well with these glasses, yes.
Hey, I see better.
Hey, here yes, yes, yes
you talk... I also bought this t-shirt.
If you speak, if you speak Italian, you can read,
you can understand what I mean.
Because I bought this shirt because it
defines me very well, it defines me very well.
Okay, sure, if not, if you're not watching,
if you're not watching the... uh, this
episode, if you're just listening to me, you
can't, you can't read what it says here.
It's a, it's a phrase in Italian that defines me,
I think it defines me a lot.
Because many, many people think
that I am a very, uh, sociable person, that
I like, that I really like being with people,
that I am, that I am very nice.
Not really, not really.
I am actually a very
unfriendly person, very unfriendly and very serious.
And a motorcycle is passing by.  It's
happened, it's happened,
a motorcycle just passed, a small motorcycle, making
a lot of noise, and I hate, hate, hate motorcycles.
Well, yes, this phrase
defines me, okay?  It defines me a lot.
People think I'm really nice, but
I'm not really nice at all.
I'm very serious and, and, and, and, well...
But it is like that, it is like that, it is like that.   The
thing is that in the
videos I have to pretend.
In the videos I have to pretend that
I like people, that I'm nice.
But no, not at all, not at all.
Well, I wanted to tell you something today,
in this, in this episode.
Um, because when I put on my
new glasses, I bought these glasses, I
put them on today for the first time, okay?
I wore them today for the first time.
This, these new glasses, has reminded me of
something I've wanted to tell you for a
long time, and I always forget.
Hm, something I always say: I have to
tell this to the guys on the, to the guys
on the podcast, and I always forget.
And with the glasses I remembered.
What I wanted to tell you, what I
wanted to tell you is that, um, you have to, you
have to look, you have to look carefully.   You have to
look, and you have to listen, you
have to listen carefully.
Above all, listening, when I say it in the
sense of, well, learning a language,
learning Spanish, in this case.  You have to
listen, you have to listen
very carefully.
That is very important.
And many of you are probably thinking:
well, sure, sure, eh, I listen, I hear,
I listen to a lot of podcasts and I watch a lot of videos.
But no, no, no, no.
Uh, what I mean is, there are a lot of people,
a lot of people who listen to my podcast and listen to or watch my
videos while, while they do other things.
While, for example, you are washing the dishes,
or while you are driving the car, or
while you are taking a walk in the park, you are
walking the dog, and in the background, hm, in the background you are listening to
my podcast or other teachers' podcasts.
And this, that's fine, that's
fine, that's fine.
Because that way you get used to the sound
of Spanish, the rhythm, the speed.
Your ear gets used
to the speed and improves,
your understanding of Spanish improves.
When someone talks to you, okay?
You will understand better because your
ear has become accustomed to Spanish.
But, but it's not enough.
That's hearing.
That's hearing.  You
don't just have to hear, you have to listen.
Hm, hear and listen are sometimes,
or very often, used
as if they were the same, okay?
As if they had the same meaning,
but in reality they are a little different.
Hearing is when you hear the traffic, the sound
of the wind, the television that is on
in the background, you hear the children playing
in the street, you hear a dog barking.   It
's not, it's hm, hearing, yes, but
without really paying attention.
Listening is voluntary.
Listening is really paying attention
to what they are saying.
So, when you want to improve your Spanish,
when you want to learn a language and improve
your way of speaking, it's not enough, it's not enough just to listen.   It's
not enough to just listen to a podcast in the background, for
example, while you're washing dishes.   It's
not enough to just listen to a video or watch
a video distractedly, right?
Oh, and have a laugh at
Juan's silly things.  It's
not enough, it's not enough.
You have to pay attention.
Watching videos in that light way, right?
And listening to podcasts in the background while you're
doing other things, while you're walking or while you
're at the gym, that's fine, that's fine.
But to really improve
you have to pay attention
to what the person is actually saying.
I'll give you an example, look.  I
'll give you an example.
Imagine if, in a podcast, I say,
"Carlos is married to Marta."
Carlos is married to Marta.
Your brain, if you're not
really paying attention—okay?—if you're
doing other things, washing the dishes,
dusting, walking the dog...
You, your brain listens—hey, your brain hears—
"Carlos... married... Marta."
Okay?
And your brain alone, with those
three words, understands.
Understand what the
podcast guy is saying, okay?   He
understands it perfectly.
The brain, due to context,
does not need to hear everything.
Understand what you're saying, okay?
And you have the impression that you have understood.
And you really understood.
You get the idea.
But really...
Could you repeat that phrase?  Would
you be able to say that phrase yourself afterwards?   I
'm not sure why...
Imagine that, in a conversation,
you want to say that Pepe is married to Pepa.
But, when you're talking, you don't remember.
You don't remember which is the correct preposition:
"Pepe married... But married to Pepa? Or to Pepa?
From Pepa? For Pepa?"
You don't remember.
You're not sure.
And maybe you're not sure whether you
say "is married" or "is married," okay?
Because you weren't paying attention, you
weren't paying attention to what the
podcast guy was actually saying, okay?
So, to remember, to remember all
those little details, it's not enough to just
listen to a podcast in the background or watch a video.
You have to pay attention, okay?
That is very important.
So I advise you, for example, to read.
Read a lot.
Because when you
're reading you can see the words, and you
can figure out what the preposition is,
what the verb is, what the article is... Right?
What is the word order?
You can read books or you can read
magazines or you can read newspapers...
Or you can just read, you can
read the transcript of a podcast.
There are many podcasts that have a transcript.
You can read what the person is saying,
and then you start to realize, you start to
realize all those little words,
all those little words, right?:
the pronouns, the prepositions...
that you normally don't pay much
attention to, but that are important.   They
are important when you want to talk.
Because it's one thing to understand—to recognize what another
person is saying—and another thing to say it yourself.
To put it another way, you have to remember.
You have to remember which is the
correct preposition, the pronouns... Well, all of that, right?
If you don't remember it well, then you have to
think, you have to doubt, you have to stop.
You have to be constantly thinking:
"Oh, what was he like? Is he married? Is he married? Was
Carlos married to Marta or with Marta?
What was he like? I don't remember..." Okay?
So, it's important, it
's important to do that.
What I also advise you is
that... look, I always carry,
I always carry a notebook here.
A notebook and a pencil, for example.
Or a pen, whatever you want.
And when you get down to it—when you get down to it,
subjunctive—when you get down to
studying Spanish, you open your notebook.   You
open your notebook, listen to a podcast, but
pay attention.  You pay attention, okay?   You
can read the transcript.
And you write some expressions that
are important to you.  Okay?  You
write them:
"Carlos is married to Marta."  Okay?
You write them.   You
do exercises with this.  You
repeat it mentally.  Yeah?
You can write a short
story, a short text.   There are
many things you can do to remember that phrase.
To remember that it is said "to be married to."
Or you can repeat it mentally.  You
can do many things.
But it is important to pay
attention to those little details.   It's
not enough, it's
not enough to simply hear in the background.
That's an attitude I've seen many times
in many people who watch YouTube videos
and think that watching videos or
listening to podcasts is enough,
is enough to learn the language.
And not.  It's not enough.  It's not enough.   I
've said it before, in other
videos, in other episodes, right?
For example, in my courses, in the
courses that I teach — Total Review,
for example, or in other courses —
there is the transcription of the podcast.
There is the transcription of
the videos and there are stories.   There
are stories where you listen, but
you also have to fill in, you have to fill in the gaps.
There are missing words, and you have to
fill in the gaps and remember
what the missing words are.
The idea is to force yourself, right?  force you to
remember the missing prepositions,
tenses, articles, and
pronouns.  No?
Anyway...
I'm getting a little
serious, aren't I?  With this topic...
And I didn't want to get so... I did
n't want to get so serious.
Well, it was something I wanted to say, wasn't it?
Hearing is not the same as listening.
Listening to a podcast is fine, but if you
want to work a little, improve your use
of prepositions, articles, all
those little words—which are very important,
all those little words are very important,
because they are very easily forgotten—then you
have to work a little more.
So you can take a
shorter podcast or a part of the podcast.
Just two or three minutes, for example,
and work only those two or three minutes.  It
is not necessary to work half an hour.  You can
work those two or three minutes.  You
can do the same
with movies, with series, right?  It
depends on your level: you can work with a
television series, a film... In short, the
important thing is to use material that you like.   It
could be a movie, it
could be a video game, right?
(Young boys like video games)
Well, with video games.   It
could be a comic.
Comics are
also fantastic for improving your language skills
because they are short sentences.
There are many expressions that are used
a lot on the street, right?  Very colloquial.
Comics are a great idea.
It's a great idea.  And, well...
Or a book.  You
don't have to read the whole book.
You can read a part, a paragraph,
and work on that paragraph.
A small section of a
newspaper too, okay?
A few lines...
Anyway.   It
's good to combine these two types of work:
an easier job, let's say, where you listen to
the podcast or watch a video
lightly, right?  without trying too hard,
just trying to understand,
and another kind of more intensive work,
where you pay more attention, right?  You
pay attention, write down
the most important expressions in your notebook,
and try to use them later in conversation.   It's
not enough to just write them down in
your notebook and nothing else, no!
Then you have to try to use them.
For example, if you go to the park, or go
shopping, or go, well, or you are at home,
in the shower, or you are vacuuming...
you can talk to yourself.
I talk to myself a lot in English.
In English.  I talk to myself a lot when
I'm alone, to practice my English.
So you can use those
expressions that you've heard
in the podcast and that you find interesting, right?  You
can repeat them, you can create stories, you can
imagine a conversation with a friend.  Yeah?
I've said this in other videos, haven't I?
Talking to yourself is
also essential to improve fluency.  Guys,
well, I don't want to ramble on any longer.  I think the
idea I wanted to tell you is clear, right?
Uh, because yes, I see that many times
students, people who study languages,
have a bit of an idea of
language learning as something a bit passive, right?
Like you sit down and, uh, the
video, you listen to a podcast or you watch
a video and your brain, let's say,
is, uh, learning all that content.
A little, a little yes.  A little bit, yes.
This is a little true, a little yes.
But let's say that if, if you want to improve, uh,
if you want to, uh, really improve fluency,
improve accuracy—accuracy which
is also important, speaking more precisely,
using the right words—then you have to
, you have to put in more effort, right?   You
have to be more active, right?  You
don't need to spend hours and hours on it, right?
A little bit every day: 10 minutes, 15
minutes a day, working on a little bit
, a few lines of a podcast, for example.
That, little by little, if you do it consistently,
h, if you do it consistently, with, with
regularity, if you do it every day
or almost every day, that will
give you very good results in the end, okay guys?
Well, we'll leave it here.
I'm, I'm getting dizzy, uh, I'm getting
a little dizzy because I'm not used to glasses,
to these glasses, and they're making me a little dizzy.
Anyway, guys, eh, we'll leave it here.
Yes, eh, as I was saying, these days are
being a bit complicated here
in Italy, for many reasons.   I do
n't want to tell you
everything, my whole life, but anyway, anyway.
Yes, some rather unpleasant things are happening to me
.
But unpleasant things have a
positive side, and that is that later I can, I
can use them in, in my, in my videos,
in my books, in my stories, right?
Well, well, it's material, it's material
for, for my, for my stories.
I've said it many times:
this podcast that I do and the videos that I make
are a bit like therapy, personal therapy.
Instead of going—now my
eyes hurt a little—instead of going,
instead of going to the psychologist, instead of going to the
psychoanalyst, I do, I do these podcasts.
And then, well, uh, it's
cheaper, it's cheaper.   I'm
talking to you, I'm telling you the things
that worry me and, well...
Well, about what's happening to me here in
Italy these days, about the problems I have,
for the moment I'm not ready, I
'm not ready to, to tell them.
But I will tell it later, in
some book, maybe in some book.
Anyway, this, uh, well, it has nothing to
do with it, it has nothing to do with what happened to me,
with what happened to me with the gorilla dog.
What happened to me with the gorilla dog,
with the gorilla dog, was tremendous.
That, that was tremendous.
That was tremendous, guys.
That was tremendous.
Someday, someday I'll tell it.
Someday, someday.
But I need to be in a better mood, I need to
be in a good mood, I need to be prepared.
And now, at this moment, I'm not,
I'm not conscious..., no, conscious, right?
How do you say?
Aware.
Aware...
Aware.   I
am not aware.  I do
n't know, I'll look it up in the dictionary later.
I'm terrible.
I'm feeling really bad these days, guys.
I'm a little... I'm a little bad, huh?
Nothing, um, well, uh, see you guys.
See you.
I'm, I'm going to rest, I'm going to rest, I'm
going to, to lie down a little, I'm going to lie down a little in,
in bed, to rest for a while.
Because I am, I am very tired.
I'm very tired.
I don't feel well.
See you, see you in the
next episode of this podcast.   See you
later, guys.  See you
later.  That's
it for today's episode.
Thank you so much for listening to the end.
If you'd like to read the transcript of this
episode or previous episodes of
our podcast, please visit our
website 1001 Reasons To Learn Spanish.
There you will also find exercises and
many resources to learn Spanish.  See you
soon!